1955年夏天，沃尔特·迪士尼遇到了一个难题。
In the summer of 1955, Walt Disney had a problem.
距离他最大胆的冒险项目开业还有几周，他必须做一个决定。
He was a few weeks off opening his most audacious venture yet,
and he had a decision to make.
>> 是装冲水马桶，还是饮水机？水管工们闹起了罢工，时间不够，两样只能选一样。
>> Should he install flushing toilets or drinking fountains? His plumbers had gone on strike, and there wasn't enough time to do both.
这是他最不需要的麻烦。
This was the last thing he needed.
他已经债台高筑，却决定不仅押上声誉，还押上个人财产，去建造一座游乐园——
He was heavily in debt and had decided to stake not just his reputation but his personal fortune on building an amusement park,
而当时的游乐园通常是免费入场的。不过他
something which was normally free to enter. But he
其实不必担心。
needn't have worried.
迪士尼将精妙的技术与银幕魔法融为一体，催生了他最具划时代意义的创新，
By combining technical wizardry with the magic of the big screen, Disney had hit upon his most consequential innovation yet,
将日渐式微的王国，打造成了一个全球帝国。
one that would transform his dwindling kingdom into a global empire.
值此迪士尼乐园七十周年之际，这便是沃尔特·迪士尼如何将银幕魔法与建造奇迹融为一体，打造出地球上最快乐之地的故事。
As Disneyland celebrates its 70th birthday, this is the story of how Walt Disney combined silvercreen magic with the miracle of construction to build the happiest place on earth.
二战结束之际，沃尔特·迪士尼陷入了困境。
At the end of World War II, Walt Disney was in a bind.
他的电影公司靠拍摄宣传片撑过了战争，
His movie studio had made it through the war making propaganda films,
但如今债务缠身，
but he was now heavily in debt,
迪士尼的辉煌岁月似乎已成过去。
and it was beginning to seem like the glory days of Disney were in the past.
但创造出世界上最著名那只老鼠的男人，还没有就此罢手。
But the man behind the world's most famous mouse wasn't done yet.
1948年，他偶然造访芝加哥的一场铁路博览会，由此燃起了对游乐设施的兴趣。
A chance visit to a railroad fair in Chicago in 1948 sparked an interest in fairground rides.
游乐园和集市在当时并不新鲜，
Amusement parks and fairs were nothing new at the time,
但在迪士尼看来，它们缺少一种独特的魔力。
but for Disney, they lacked a certain magic.
通常，这些地方都是围绕游乐设施来设计的，场景布置和装饰只是点缀，谈不上什么创意构想。
Usually, they were designed around the rides with some attention given to scene setting and decoration, but nothing resembling any kind of creative vision.
迪士尼想要创造出全新的东西——一个有游乐设施和景点的地方，但不止于此，它还要真正讲述一个故事。
Disney wanted to create something new, a place with rides and attractions, but more than that, a place that would really tell a story.
他想呈现一个理想世界的形象，纯真而美好，让孩子们的想象力可以自由飞翔。
He wanted to project an image of an idyllic world, one of innocence and wholesomeness, where children could let their imaginations run free.
为了让这个想法落地，迪士尼请来了艺术总监赫布·莱曼。
To get his idea off the ground, Disney called in art director Herb Ryman.
在1953年9月一个忙碌的周末里，两人共同构建出了迪士尼乐园的初步概念。
And over the course of a frantic weekend in September 1953, they developed the initial concept for Disneyland.
他们所创造的，是与以往任何事物都截然不同的东西。
What they created was something radically different to anything that had come before.
第一个重大突破，在于布局设计。
The first major difference came in the layouts.
迪士尼在考察其他游乐园时发现，它们的一大弱点是往往缺乏整体规划，
When researching other parks, Disney found that one of their weaknesses was they often lacked a coherent plan,
导致游客在园内迷失方向。
making them pretty confusing to navigate.
如果要打造地球上最快乐的地方，游园路线就必须简单易懂。
If he were to create the happiest place on earth, it would have to be simple to get around.
为此，迪士尼必须精心设计人流动线，同时统筹布置各类景点。
And to do that, Disney had to meticulously design the flow of people as well as the attractions.
而这一切，都从入口开始。
And that all began at the entrance.
当时，美国的游乐园通常免费入场，因此设有多个入口。而迪士尼乐园
At the time, amusement parks in the US were typically free to enter and as such had multiple entrances. Disneyland,
却只有一个。通过这种方式限制进入，
however, would have just one. By restricting access to the park in this way,
迪士尼得以从游客踏入乐园的那一刻起，便为他们打造一段精心策划的体验之旅。
Disney was able to create a tightly curated experience from the moment guests stepped foot in his park.
游客首先会看到一道路堤，上方设有一座小型铁路站台，
Visitors would be greeted by an embankments on which sat a station for a miniature railway
铁路环绕整个乐园运行。
that ran the perimeter of the entire park.
这道路堤还隐藏着乐园的第一个幻觉——
This would also conceal the park's first illusion.
它同时充当实体屏障，将外部世界的声音和景象隔绝在外。
The embankment doubling as a physical barrier to prevent the sights and sounds of the outside world from getting in.
穿过路堤，游客将经由一条隧道进入园区。迪士尼将其称为"舞台幕布"，
From there, they would enter the park via a tunnel which Disney called the stage curtains,
隧道入口处的一块小铭牌，标志着游客告别现实世界、踏入迪士尼想象王国的那一刻。
a small plaque marking the point at which guests left the real world behind and entered Disney's imagination.
进入乐园后的第一站是美国大街——一个理想化的美式街景，大量取材自迪士尼的家乡，密苏里州的马瑟林镇。
First stop after entering was Main Street USA, an idolized version of the American High Street, heavily based on Disney's hometown of Marceline in Missouri.
从这里起，乐园将运用一系列引人注目的视觉元素来引导游客——
From there, the park would make use of eye-catching visual elements, which Disney would coin as weenies,
迪士尼将其称为"视觉诱饵"（weenies，迪士尼自创的行业术语）。
to pull people around the park.
其中最壮观的，自然是一座奇幻城堡。
The grandest of these would, of course, be a fantasy castle,
它将吸引游客走向中央广场——一个辐射状的枢纽，乐园中的每一片区域、每一项游乐设施和景点都从这里向外延伸。
which would draw visitors towards a central plaza, the hub from which every land, ride, and attraction would radiate out.
这里不仅让游览路线更清晰，也为游客提供了一个相聚和休憩的场所。
As well as making navigation easier, it would create a point at which people could meet and rest.
从广场向外延伸出多个主题区域。
Branching off from this were a series of themed areas.
其他游乐园也常有一些新奇的建筑来营造异域风情，但那些不过是独立的亮点，而非统一主题的一部分。
Other parks had often included novelty buildings to give a sense of the exotic, but these would be standalone features rather than part of a coherent theme.
迪士尼的计划，是打造全方位的沉浸式体验。
What Disney planned was total immersion.
就像整个乐园本身一样，每片区域在视觉上都与可能破坏沉浸感的外界事物隔绝开来。
Just like the park itself, each land would be visually cut off from anything that might spoil the illusion.
概念草图完成后，迪士尼派他的兄弟罗伊前往纽约，为项目建设筹集资金。
With the concept sketches complete, Disney sent his brother Roy off to New York to raise money for the build.
但如何将如此新颖独特的构想变为现实？
But how do you turn something this new and unique into a reality?
迪士尼从未有过如此大规模的建造经验，更遑论打破如此多先例。
Disney had no experience in building anything on this scale, let alone something that broke with this much precedent.
他明白，单靠想象力是行不通的。
He figured relying purely on imagination would get him nowhere.
但纯粹的工程技术，又未免枯燥乏味。
But engineering on its own wasn't very entertaining.
他需要的是能将艺术创意与实际技能融为一体、创造出独一无二作品的人。他需要的，是幻想工程师（Imagineer——迪士尼将"想象力"与"工程师"合而为一的创意称谓）。
He needed people who could combine artistic creativity with practical skills to create something unique. What he needed was an imagineer.
幸运的是，好莱坞正是这类人才的聚集地。
Fortunately, Hollywood was full of them.
他从自己公司的布景设计师和艺术家中广招人才，也从一个强劲的对手那里挖角。
He turned to set designers and artists in his own company, but also from a powerful rival.
20世纪福克斯公司拥有一个面积是迪士尼乐园四倍的外景地，
20th Century Fox had a back lot four times the size of Disneyland.
里面聚集着大量布景艺术家，从城市街道到蒸汽船，什么都能建。
And it was filled with scenic artists used to building everything from city streets to steamboats.
迪士尼正是从这里，为他的幻想工程师大军补充了大批生力军。
It was from here that Disney filled the ranks of his new army of imagineers.
设计流程从一份提案开始，再逐步发展为故事板，
The design process started with a pitch which was then worked up into storyboards
进而演变为由小到大、层层递进的实体模型。
and further on into models of increasing sizes.
整个过程灵活机动，历经反复修改和调整，就连乐园中一些体量最大的建筑，也不例外。
The whole process was fluid with constant revisions and alterations made throughout, including on some of the park's biggest structures.
这是德国南部的新天鹅堡，它正是
This is Nushmanstein Castle in southern Germany. It was used as the inspiration
标志性的睡美人城堡的灵感来源，城堡矗立在乐园的核心位置。
for the iconic Sleeping Beauty Castle which lays at the head of the park.
它有城门楼、角楼和宫殿，这些都为迪士尼版本的城堡提供了参考蓝本。
It has a gate house, turrets, and palace, all of which provided a reference for Disney's version.
宫殿正面设有一处阳台，通向气派的歌手大厅。
On the front of the palace, it has a balcony which leads from the spectacular Singer's Hall.
这一细节最初出现在设计图中，却在一次颇具戏剧性的意外中被改变——这恰恰说明，整个开发过程有多么灵活。
This detail was initially included in the plans, but in a sign of how fluid the development was, it was changed purely by chance.
在设计阶段，工程师们曾将模型拆开清洁，却在沃尔特·迪士尼突然来访时匆忙将其重新拼装。
During the design phase, engineers had taken the model apart for cleaning, only to quickly reassemble it when Walt Disney came to visit.
慌乱之中，他们把宫殿装反了方向。
In the rush, they put the palace back on the wrong way round.
迪士尼发现了这个错误，却反而更喜欢这个效果，于是就按照模型拼错的样子建造了城堡。
Disney noticed the mistake, but actually preferred the way it looked and had the castle built as the model stood.
那处阳台至今仍在，只是移到了城堡的背面。
The balcony still lives on today, but at the back of the castle.
这种随机应变的精神，并不止步于设计阶段。
This level of improvisation didn't stop at the design stage.
丛林巡游已成为迪士尼乐园最受欢迎的游乐项目之一，并已在其他迪士尼乐园中复制落地。
The Jungle Cruise has become one of the most popular rides of Disneyland and has since been replicated at other Disney parks.
如今设计这样一个项目，需要庞大的团队历经数月的策划与设计。
Designing a ride like this today requires months of planning and design work by huge teams of people.
但回到1954年，这个项目的整体路线规划，完全出自传奇艺术总监哈珀·戈夫一人之手。
But back in 1954, the ride's layout was solely down to this man, legendary art director Harper Goff.
在一名推土机司机的注视下，戈夫拿起一根树枝，沿着项目地块走了一圈，在土地上划出一道线。
With a bulldozer driver looking on, Goff took a stick and walked around the ride's plot, drawing a line in the soil.
走完之后，他又在几米外平行地划出另一道线。
Once completed, he drew a parallel line a few meters away.
推土机随即跟进，将挖出的泥土堆上两侧路堤——丛林巡游的路线布局，就这样大功告成。
The bulldozer followed, piling up the excavated soil on the embankments, and the layout of the jungle cruise was complete.
这听起来也许有点像自由爵士——随性而为，但事关重大。
Now, this might all sound a bit free jazz, but there was a lot at stake.
如果迪士尼搞砸了，他将血本无归。
If Disney didn't pull this off, he stood to lose everything.
随着迪士尼对乐园的野心不断膨胀，所需的资金也水涨船高。
As Disney's ambitions for the park grew, so did the bill to pay for it all.
动工之时，他已举债1700万美元，
By the time construction began, he'd taken out $17 million in loans,
按今天的购买力折算，相当于逾6亿美元。
equivalent to over $600 million today.
他甚至将个人财产押了进去，变卖房产、兑现人寿保险来筹措资金。
He even put his personal fortune on the line, selling properties and cashing in his life insurance to raise funds.
1954年，资金已经到位。
In 1954, he had the financing in place.
但面对如此巨大的风险，
But with so much money at stake,
他需要乐园尽快开始盈利，这意味着必须赶在来年夏天旅游旺季到来之前开门迎客。
he needed the park earning as soon as possible, and that meant opening the gates in the lucrative vacation season the following summer.
1954年7月16日，距盛大开幕整整一年零一天，迪士尼乐园正式破土动工。
On the 16th of July 1954, a year and a day before the grand opening, Disneyland broke ground.
为了协助幻想工程师精英团队，迪士尼招入了两位关键人物统筹建设工作：科尼利厄斯·范德比尔特·伍德与乔·福勒。
To supplement his crack squad of imagineers, Disney brought in two crucial figures to oversee the construction.
伍德是一位精明的商人，在组织协调方面极具眼光。
Cornelius Vanderbilt Wood and Joe Fowler. Wood was a savvy businessman with a keen eye for organization.
正是他找到了迪士尼乐园的建设用地——
It was he who had found the site that Disneyland was going to be built on,
加利福尼亚州阿纳海姆160英亩的橙子园和核桃园。
160 acres of orange and walnut groves in Anaheim, California.
当时的阿纳海姆还是一座偏僻的农业小镇，但其平坦的地势非常适合施工，
At the time, Anaheim was a rural farming town, but its flat land was perfect for constructing on.
而新建的高速公路又让洛杉矶市区近在咫尺，仅需30分钟车程。
and access to the recently constructed freeway meant downtown Los Angeles was just 30 minutes away.
伍德曾在通用动力公司任职，负责培训建造飞机的工人团队，
Wood had previously worked at General Dynamics, training teams of people to build airplanes,
很快便着手组织每天涌入工地的数千名工人。
and he soon sang about organizing the thousands of workers that came to this site every day.
福勒则是一位退役海军上将，身经二战风雨。他
Fowler, meanwhile, was a retired admiral and a veteran of both World Wars. He'd
在过去数十年间，一直主持为海军建造军舰。
spent the last few decades overseeing the construction of warships for the Navy.
最初，他被调来负责马克·吐温号蒸汽船的建造，
Initially, he'd been drafted in to oversee the construction of the Mark Twain steamboat,
但他卓越的后勤统筹能力使他在整个乐园的建设工作中都成了不可或缺的核心人物。
but his ability to wrangle logistics made him invaluable to the wider construction effort of the park.
福勒最初对施工计划的评估相当悲观：计划在开幕日前准备就绪的20个景点中，只有6个能如期完工；
Fowler's initial assessment of the plans was bleak. Of the 20 attractions due to be ready for opening day, only six were going to get there.
11个存疑；另有3个肯定赶不上。
11 were doubtful, and three would definitely not be ready in time.
福勒和伍德共同确立了一套策略——优先保障乐园叙事性强的核心体验，
Together, Fowler and Wood adopted a strategy that prioritized the important storytelling aspects of the park while
同时在其他方面想办法压缩成本、提高效率。
finding ways to cut corners and find efficiencies elsewhere.
他们的目标不是追求完美，
Their aim wasn't perfection.
而是争分夺秒，让一切在开幕日前达到"足够好"的状态，后续再持续完善。
Instead, they raced to get everything good enough for opening day with a view to continue work afterwards.
种植区周围的护栏被取消；
Handrails around planted areas were scrapped.
工地原有农场上砍下的核桃树，被截去树冠，倒置重新种回地里，用来模拟红树林沼泽的景观。
Walnut trees felled from the site's original farm were kept, cut off at the trunk, and then replanted upside down to resemble mangrove swamps.
但在这些节省成本和随机应变的背后，也诞生了一些真正令人叹服的创新。
But among the cost-saving and improvisation, there were some truly impressive innovations.
你有没有留意到这根护柱或这道围栏有什么特别之处？
Do you notice anything special about this bolard or this fence?
或许走过的时候，你根本什么都没注意到。
Well, it might be that as you're walking through, you don't notice anything at all.
尽管迪士尼团队竭尽全力，却始终无法将外部世界完全屏蔽在外。
Despite their best efforts, Disney's team wasn't able to banish the outside world completely.
垃圾桶、管线设施这类东西，并不在童话剧本里，却是乐园不可或缺的一部分。
Things like rubbish bins and utilities weren't part of the fantasy script, but were still essential to the park.
为此，他的幻想工程师们调配出一种新颜色，让这些不讨喜的设施融入园内绿化景观。
To solve this, his imagineers created a new color that would help unwanted features blend in with the planting scheme around the park.
他们将这种颜色命名为"消隐绿"。
They named it Go Away Green.
这一创意大获成功，时至今日仍在各大迪士尼乐园广泛使用，甚至还衍生出了"升级版"。
It was so successful that it's still widely used in Disney parks today and even has a successor.
凡是需要融入天空背景的物体，则涂上"消隐蓝"。
Things meant to blend into the sky are painted blending blue.
但迪士尼幻想工程师们有一项技术，被证明是乐园中最成功的视觉幻术之一。
But there was one technique Disney's Imagineers used
that proved to be one of the most successful illusions of the park.
美国大街的设计，是为了以那种质朴、纯真的美国风情迎接八方游客。
Main Street USA is designed to welcome visitors into that quaint, wholesome vision of Americana.
但用不了多久，你就能发现其中的电影魔法：每栋建筑只有底层是真正使用的空间，
But it doesn't take long to spot the movie magic at work here. Only the ground floor of each building is occupied because
因为上层楼面缩小，无法实际使用。这正是因为整条街都运用了强迫透视法。
the upper floors are too small.
That's because the whole street uses forced perspective.
这一技术长期被好莱坞所采用——
The technique has long been used in Hollywood
布景以扭曲的角度建造，在摄影棚内制造出纵深感或高度感的错觉。
where sets are built at distorted angles to create the illusion of depth or height in a studio.
在《黑卫士》的这个场景中，一幅彩绘背景板营造出通往天堂的阶梯，而身材较矮的演员被安排站在台阶高处，进一步强化了这种错觉。
In this scene from the Black Guards, a painted backdrop creates the staircase to heaven, and shorter actors were hired to stand up the steps, furthering the illusion.
按真实比例建造一条美式街道，超出了迪士尼的财力所及。
Building a life-size American high street was beyond even Disney's means.
但等比例缩小，又只会让街道显得局促。
But shrinking everything would just make the street look small.
于是，建筑物被建造成不同的尺寸比例：
Instead, the buildings were constructed to a range of sizes with
底层接近1:1的实际比例，一楼和二楼则依次按更小的比例建造。
ground floors built at near 1:1 scale and the first and second floors built at increasingly smaller scales.
楼层越高，建筑高度缩减越明显，我们的眼睛便会误以为它们距离更远，进而认为建筑比实际更高。
By decreasing the height of a building the higher it gets, our eyes are tricked into thinking they're further away, and we assume they're taller than they are.
而强迫透视法最精彩的运用，莫过于标志性的睡美人城堡。
But the most effective use of force perspective is on the iconic Sleeping Beauty Castle.
城堡最高处距地面23米，比白宫还略高一些。
The tallest tip of the castle rises 23 m off the ground, making it slightly taller than the White House.
体量可观，却不像真正的堡垒那般高耸压迫。
So big, but not a towering fortress.
为了让城堡看起来更加高大，与美国大街如出一辙，每一层都按略小的比例建造。
To make it appear bigger, like Main Street, each story is built at a slightly smaller scale.
而大量高低错落、互不相连的设计元素，更进一步强化了这种视觉效果。
But that effect is enhanced by introducing so many disconnected elements, all of a different height.
正因为没有统一的楼层高度可供参照，大脑失去了判断它应有高度的基准，城堡因此显得愈发高耸。
Because there are no consistent stories, our brain has less of a reference for how tall it should be, making the castle seem bigger.
1955年7月17日，经过一年的紧张建设，见证真相的时刻终于到来——
On July 17th, 1955, after a year of frantic construction, the moment of truth had arrived.
迪士尼乐园开幕日。
The opening day of Disneyland.
>> 向所有来到这片欢乐之地的朋友们，致以欢迎。
>> To all who come to this happy place, welcome.
>> 一切都在向这一刻汇聚。数千名宾客受邀出席，
>> Everything had been building up to this moment. Thousands of guests were invited.
现场电视直播万事俱备。这将是迪士尼的高光时刻吗？
A live TV broadcast was scheduled.
Would this be Disney's moment of triumph?
然而，并不是。整件事简直是一场彻头彻尾的灾难。
Well, no. The whole thing was a total disaster.
大批伪造门票在外流通，园区被汹涌的人潮淹没。
The park was swamped with people after thousands of counterfeit tickets were sold.
正如乔·福勒所预言的，许多游乐设施尚未完工，而已完工的大多数也相继出现故障。
Just as Joe Fowl had predicted, many of the rides weren't finished,
and most of those that were ended up breaking down.
城堡附近发生燃气泄漏，几乎将其付之一炬；马克·吐温号则因登船人数过多，险些沉没。
A gas leak near the castle nearly burned it to the ground and the Mark Twain almost sank with the amount of people boarding it.
>> 喂，艾琳。>> 你好吗？我这边快撑不住了。
>> Hello, Irene. >> How are you? My is lifting.
>> 至于那些罢工的水管工——沃尔特最终选择优先完工马桶，而非饮水机，
>> As for the striking plumbers, Walt had opted to finish the toilets on time rather than the drinking fountains,
结果引来外界指责，认为他是在故意逼人花钱买饮料，而不愿提供免费饮水。
leading people to accuse him of a cynical ploy to buy drinks instead of providing free water.
但归根结底，这些都无关紧要。
But ultimately, none of that mattered.
就像近三十年前他的第一批动画片那样，迪士尼乐园牢牢抓住了大众的想象力。此后，乐园的建设工作从未停歇，游乐设施也在随后数年间持续升级改进。
Just as his first cartoons had done nearly 30 years earlier, Disneyland had captured the public imagination.
Work on the park went on and over the following years, rides were continuously improved.
尽管成人票价高达1美元、儿童票50美分，
Despite the princely entrance fee of $1 for adults and 50 cents for children,
开幕后短短两个月内，就有100万人造访了这座乐园。
within 2 months of opening, 1 million people had visited the park.
迪士尼乐园已成为一个标志性的存在。
Disneyland had become so iconic that
1959年，苏联最高领导人访问美国期间，公开表达了他和夫人对未能参观迪士尼乐园的遗憾与失望。
on a trip to America in 1959, the president of the USSR expressed his and his wife's disappointment that they were barred from visiting.
就迪士尼本人而言，他对迪士尼乐园始终不曾完全满意。
For his part, Disney was never completely satisfied with Disneyland.
带着从中汲取的经验与教训，他很快将目光投向了更大的目标——在佛罗里达打造一个更宏大、更完善的版本。
And with the lessons he'd learned, he quickly turned his attention to building a bigger, better version in Florida.
沃尔特·迪士尼在有生之年，未能亲眼见证他下一个作品的落成。
Walt Disney passed away before he could ever see the completion of his next creation.
但华特迪士尼世界最终证明了自己，成为有史以来规模最大、最为精致复杂的主题乐园之一。
But Walt Disney World would prove to be one of the biggest and most sophisticated theme parks ever built.
七十年过去，开幕日的种种狼狈早已被淡忘。
70 years on, the rough edges of opening day are long forgotten.
留存下来的，是沃尔特留下的那份蓝图——一个以好莱坞的手法为工具、以工程的严谨为骨架、以独一无二的想象力为灵魂所建造的地方。
What endures is the blueprint that Walt created.
A place built with the tools of Hollywood, the discipline of engineering, and an imagination all of his own.
迪士尼乐园不只是让他的电影公司重焕生机，
Disneyland didn't just revive his studio.
更是重新书写了我们设计体验、塑造城市乃至构建整个世界的方式。
It rewrote the playbook for how we design experiences, cities, and even entire worlds.
别忘了，我们正通过对Brick Borrow的投资，为下一代建造者带去启发——这是一项出色的乐高订阅服务。
Don't forget that we're inspiring the next generation of builders through our investment into Brick Borrow, a fantastic LEGO subscription service.
欢迎前往brickbarrow.com了解更多信息，立即开启你的乐高之旅。
You can learn more and get started today over at brickbarrow.com.
一如既往，如果你喜欢这个视频，想要获取更多来自顶尖建筑视频频道的内容，记得订阅B1M。
And as always guys, if you enjoyed this video and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction, make sure you subscribe to the B1M.